Sorry, this week 10 and we are discussing structured probabilistic models for deep learning.
The central question is how can we represent uncertainty in relationships among variables
using graphs.
This is the central question for today's lecture and there are several things that we will
discuss, first is module 9 recap, probability distribution, Bayes theorem, you may be already
aware of the Bayes theorem, then structured probabilistic models, how they work, conditional
independence, directed and undirected models, how Bayesian networks in connection with deep
learning it has and we will close the session with some reflection and some critic activities.
Okay, I think I am presenting yes, I am presenting correct, but just bear with me, this is with
module 9 that we discussed with respect to the module 9.
So the primary question, first question is what is the representation in machine learning?
So representation in machine learning, we discussed last week about the representation
and its importance and we discussed several aspects of representation and we discussed
that representation is not a measure of training time, it is not a fixed prediction produced
by a model and it's not a deleting, but it is a way of describing or encoding data and
then what is the main purpose of representation learning?
It is to remove the need for model evaluation, to decrease the size of the raw dataset, to
manually select every feature, to automatically discover useful features from data, what is
the main purpose of representation learning, I think would be the correct answer, to automatically
discover useful features from data proof and then which model learns a compressed latent
representation through reconstruction, which model do you think is the correct one, A,
auto-encoders, yeah perfect, these are not the options, which statement about learned
representation is correct, learning representation, usefulness depends on the task and learning
objectives, yes, okay so do you have any question regarding assessment 3, do you have any specific
concern regarding assessment 3 or anything you would like to know, so I may have missed
the last class, so I don't think there was a discussion about this, actually that was
the last class, but I did not think there was a discussion about this, the marks for
assessment 2 has already been released, sorry marks for assessment 2, it has already been
released, no, no, no, okay, yeah I will mark in a day or two, so yeah I have not yet released
marks for assessment 2, and assessment 3 is basically is a group task, a report and source
code should be submitted and due by the end of week 12, Wednesday in total weightage is
40%, so in assessment 2 your task was to present research project along with 5 to 7 minutes
of individual seminar and couple of groups presented during the class, others you should
have submitted recorded version, in assessment 3 you will implement that project based on
deep learning principles, you will produce a professional report detailing the entire
implementation process, including clear list of requirements or functionalities, steps
taken to address those requirements and the deep learning principles considered for the
implementation, the methods used and an analysis of the outcomes, so the aim of this assessment
is to gain implementation experience of a deep learning project concerning a life, real
life issue, so some of you, one of the projects was predicting, one of the project was related
to agriculture and the other project was presented based on sentiment analysis but with variable
probability because if there are sentences with positive and negative aspects, so you
are going to prepare 1500 word report and this report, you should write a report based
on your whole process, means what you plan, how the steps were taken because you should
have a data and you will process the data, what outcome you achieve, what output you
achieved and before that even what is the data set itself, describe the data set and
then what libraries you are using, bring those libraries in the report and how the data set
look like, you can put a header of the data set, maybe header from the Python into the
report and then what libraries you are using into it and which algorithms you have chosen
to make use of and then training part and then testing part and how data sets were divided
and in the testing phase you have to show results, clear results, aid them into the
report step by step, whatever the results you have achieved and what parameters were
used and if you have made some changes into the parameters what was the effect and finally
your conclusion and your overall opinion and learning.
So what I am trying to say, your report should not be just a linear straight forward some
commentary but there should be steps, step by step things, what you did, what you achieved,
what went wrong, how did you achieve the better results and what were the parameters so everything
that could tell the overall process of what you have done instead of general final outcome.
So it should be 1500 word report concise summary of the previous assessment you can present
your report using instead of writing format of the cover page state the word count I don't
mind if you add 1800 to 2000 words I don't mind but if you put everything step by step
along with the snapshots from the Python code with the results and it would be excellent.
Application instruction you can submit word file better you submit the word file as I
can add or PDF file whichever you prefer academic integrity declaration you have to sign and
assessment attributes a completeness and efficiency is one of the attributes we did 20% all of
the major requirements have been implemented the system functions properly exceptions are
handled very well coding convention and quality of code the code is exactly written there
are no more than two errors in the terms of the naming conventions I usually run the code
I usually try to download the code and check it's working and so on I believe at this stage
you are very mature and your responses regarding the code would be excellent but now the interpretation
of the results and the steps that you have taken the overall process that you will put
it into the report would be evaluated based on the integration of knowledge topic for
depth of discussion this will be based on your report and communication overall would
be that's what I am saying means a step by step things you have added into documentation
so these things are 30% is almost that how you are presenting your findings into the
report or how you are putting your findings into the report and the challenges you have
faced and results you achieved and why if the results were poor why it for poor justifications
are rational so yeah this is all about the assessment three and I'm happy to answer your
question if you have any or if you are feeling any difficulty or if you want to clarify anything
then feel free to ask okay with the assessment oh good thank you so now with respect to today's
topic for example we have to diagnose we have a medical diagnosis in problem under uncertainty
then suppose a patient has fewer cough and fatigue and the positive test result and history
of exposure and there are combination of issues like fever cough and fatigue and as it is
positive so you want to develop a probabilistic you want to predict estimate the disease based
on the probabilistic model so the same system symptoms may have several causes and not every
patient shows every symptom so test result may be imperfect and some relevant information
may be unknown so what is the main idea the main idea is basically you are trying to develop
a holistic probabilistic best model for GP then you have to understand how you represent
these relationships and uncertainties clearly because your model is working with the guidance
of doctor or your model can be working independently so they should not diagnose something that
is irrelevant so what could be the structure behind the variables so there could be one
possible structure could be exposure disease and symptoms expires already there and there
is a identified disease and that can reveal the symptoms there is a disease and it could
be identified by test result our test results can bring there is disease so variables are
not treated as an unrelated list so what we are trying to figure out we are trying to
figure out what is the relationship among disease and symptoms and then final conclusion
so for a structure based solution there are some ways to represent them and that one way
is graphical models that make the structure of uncertainty visible so why structure help
us because the structure can tell you the indirect directly and which variables depend
on others and how evidence changes probabilities and which relationships need to be modeled
because our not every relationship could be producing a significant result so in such
cases graphical model could be helpful and that structure probabilistic models are basically
the graphical models describe a probability distribution using a graph so the graphical
model is basically the sum of probability theory plus graph theory and these graphical
models are in fact a language for representing complete relationship among many variables
for example so what is the graphical model this graphical model what is in the graphical
model in graphical model there could be nodes there could be edges and there could be missing
edges are you using are we using graphical model anywhere in our daily life any idea
do you know where the graphical models are being used most often GPS maybe GPS is using
graphical models because graphical model is in fact used where for the relationship mostly
with how two things are related to each other maybe you check for the GPS I was thinking
about yes sorry I was thinking about for example if we want to go from point A to point B we
maybe it would be used to calculate faster route that was my thought at least such algorithms
are used for GPS but you can check on the graphical models yeah it's a good idea means
a relationship among the cities and destinations you are thinking in that way
I mean most of the time it would be for medical applications diagnosis as well that yeah medical
applications yes yeah I doubt is yeah so maybe if they have couple of symptoms what's the
relationship of the end diagnosis that kind of relationship yeah even Facebook may be
using this graphical models oh yeah what about like dating apps like tinder or bumble they
use this as well so maybe if you write down what kind of attributes your you prefer the
might sort of match it up with similar attributes being sick by others notice basically you
are a node and there can be too many other nodes B C D and based on your network they
can advise you which person you would like to connect because you are seeing the recommendations
on Facebook that this is the most relevant person with you this means common friends
based on that because oh you have you have a connection with someone and then someone
has a common common entities and then they are telling you you should connect with this
person and so on so yeah what about Netflix like the suggestions on Netflix yeah based
on history yeah they are the recommendation systems yes in recommendation systems so you
should also check how these recommendation systems may be related to the graph theory
because in those recommendation systems you are being recommended with different types
of movies or stories based on your prayer of history so yeah okay now in understanding
this probabilistic models and the basic probability I have added few slides on the basic probability
I think you may be already aware of these things like a conditional probability is what
is the probability of a given B means B is known is unknown so it is a joint probability
divided by the marginal probability for example we have one example joint probability of for
example X is a disease and Y is a symptom and we are finding disease with the symptoms
so joint probability of X means disease is 0 comma Y is 0 is 0.5 so this is the thing
joint probability but if you find conditional probability means what is the probability
that disease is X given conditions are Y conditions are symptoms sorry so for example if you say
what is the probability that disease is 0 means 0 means no toothache or no headache
whatever you say one means headache so what is the probability that there is no headache
given that Y symptom is one something like that no toothache if the symptom is one one
means test result may be something like that so if X is 0 given that Y is 1 so X is 0 given
that Y is 1 result is 0.1 that is the joint probability and marginal probability is the
whole thing so the probability of X means no toothache Y condition is output is one
is 0.25 means it is 25 percent time a 25 percent chance so this is basically a way of calculating
the probability I'm not going further into detail anything and I added this slide Bayes
theorem because it's basically based on Bayes and other experts so Bayes theorem is basically
worldwide renowned approach for computing the probability with with an additional belief
or additional information and Bayes theorem is highly admired in probabilistic models
because it's adding the evidence calculating the evidence adding the evidence and generating
or finding the or proofing the belief so for example what is the probability of A given
B and Bayes theorem says probability of B given A means and probability of A and probability
of B so what is the probability of disease given that it is a positive test so it means
if you want to check if this is a disease and given the positive test depends on how
common the disease is and how likely a positive result is when the disease is present and
how frequently positive results occur overall it means the evidence changes our belief about
an uncertain event so Bayes theorem is basically a theorem that is used to find out whatever
your belief is statistically means Bayesian statistics often refers to probabilities as
representing beliefs or opinions about a proposition kind of statement that can be true or false
for example the third world war will be in x year this is your belief or you can say
the next pandemic will be in C years or you are Duan this is your belief then you can
prove your belief by the help of Bayesian theorem with marginal probabilities and known
probability conditional probability results and it's not necessary you can prove it but
you can keep calculating the keep collecting the evidence and can prove it so for example
this is B of A this and this is A of B given A what is the B so if probability of puppy
given cute and probability of cute given puppy they both are not same so what does it mean
what is the probability of cute given puppy there is 95% probability that puppy is given
then it should be cute 95% but what is the probability of puppy given cute or maybe low
probability because if something is good not necessarily it should be puppies I hope it
makes sense and there is a chain rule of probability where you have to find random variables probabilities
with different conditions like probability of x1 x2 x3 x4 then it is calculated based
on some assumptions with a joint probability without assumptions this can become complicated
as the number of variables increases so graphical model is used to simplify the expression of
identifying which variables depend directly on another so this is how it works so probability
of x1 given x2 x3 x4 x2 on x3 x4 this is x3 to x4 and x4 to be honest I don't have proper
other slides that can explain how you are going to summarize in for random variables
computation of these probabilities are in it is to be honest beyond the scope of this
lecture as well this is just I have added few basic probability rules just as we can
move ahead now what is the conditional independence for example there is a disease like a fever
and there is a disease a cough so if we say they are conditionally independent means we
can say fever and cough may be related because both depend on the disease but once the disease
is known either fever or cough we may assume fever has no relationship with cough given
the disease means conditional independence means fever is conditionally independent of
cough given the disease this is some way of exclusively treating two things separately
okay any questions or anything you would like to clarify
is everyone okay okay take maybe five minutes break and then we will continue thanks
you
so let us discuss where does the structure help we need a structure because without the
structure of full joint distribution can require a very large number of probabilities but with
the structure we can represent conditional independence assumptions supporting inference
about unknown variables supporting efficient learning and this structure is producing representation
only direct dependencies and easier to inspect so these are few of the advantages but there
are two ways to represent the structure of graphical models one is directed graph and
other is undirected graphical models and in directed graphical models it uses arrows for
relationship like there was a disease and there was something so these arrows are used
often called Bayesian networks and in undirected graphical models there are edges there is
no arrows and often called Markov random fields they have a conditional dependencies but they
have a mutual compatibility or association the two nodes and can represent directional
processes can be useful when direction is unclear or unnecessary undirected graph and
must not contain directed cycles may contain cycles means there is a neighboring mutual
understanding or mutual association it uses conditional probabilities because it has a
Bayesian network and commonly use potential functions so which model should be used it
depends upon the conditions and assumptions that you are making use of so a Bayesian network
is a directed graphical model it contains a directed cyclic graph for example disease
is a fever and disease has been identified by a test result or requires a test result
means favor fever or any other thing that requires a test result so the arrow shows
how the probability distribution is factorized so an arrow represent the probabilistic dependency
our disease can be identified by a test result so it does not automatically prove a cause
for example disease is a fever and disease a requires a test result so the joint distribution
becomes probability of disease whereas the probability of fever given disease and probability
of test result given disease so instead of modeling every combination separately the
network uses some other local distributions and try to identify the actual cause and effect
so what is the cause and what is the effect so there is maybe a cause maybe like a viral
or something and disease can be in effect that they have a fever and it is identified
by test result so you have to have an inference means identifying the effect of based on the
cause means you are trying to determine the evidence to estimate unknown variables unknown
variable is whether it is a disease or not based on some cause and it can be verified
by test results so probability of disease given symptoms or probability of failed component
given sensor readings so failed component is a effect based on the cause that is sorry
yeah there was a effect related to the cause and it was identified proof based on the evidence
of sensor reading and probably of world label given surrounding words and probably of fraud
given transition behavior so there was an effect of fraud based on some issues and then
it was identified by a behavior so observed evidence update probabilities and estimate
unknown variables so inference in a Bayesian network is basically talking about what we
have observed what should we now believe so Bayesian network is very good in proving your
belief based on further evidence as much as evidences are added Bayesian network will
keep working and will sum up all the new evidences and update the probability in the result whereas
undirected graph it doesn't produce any direct relationship it has edges like this one so
it connects related variable without specifying a direction it says there is a relationship
between cause and effect but does not necessarily identify what is what is that relationship
so relationships are mutual causal direction is not required neighboring variables should
have compatible values so the problem contains special or sequential relationships for example
neighboring image regions may have a relationship but it would not be telling explicitly connected
words or labels they could have a relationship social networks they could have a relationship
for example if I am getting a feed for many of my colleagues who are working in a same
institute or I have graduated from some in university then it would be giving me a right
of vision that you should connect with this person are based on my connections like we
have a mutual five six connections and it will be giving me that this person are based
on my post if it could be giving that this person could be relevant you should also be
receiving such kind of notifications isn't it in molecular interactions so this is undirected
graphical models and the probabilities in undirected models is determined by this relationship
so probability of x is equal to one upon z that is z normalizes the scores and sum of
phi of k and x of k this is basically phi of k is measures compatibility among related
variables and x is your input so the product combined local relationship so higher potential
indicates a more compatible configuration so directed graph is using probability but
this undirected graph model is using potential functions to determine the relationship among
different variables now this is one learning activity I would appreciate if you could contribute
in which activity we should use directed graph and which activity we should use undirected
graph so you can just say one for example undirected or directed graph two undirected
or directed graph three same so can you please contribute in the chat which activity do you
think should be directed graph and which activity should be undirected graph for example undirected
or directed you can just write in the chat to undirected or directed undirected or directed
undirected or directed directed undirected or directed just choose one option for each
activity and just write into the chat and then we can discuss is this okay I take maybe
few minutes you can write your response and then we can discuss
you
which one is correct Lewis Harr no mayor disease influencing symptoms
symptoms this is a directed Lewis because it has a relationship we have been discussing
under Bayesian network this in disease influencing symptoms are you listening Lewis yeah I got
a little bit confused with that one thinking that maybe one disease or multiple disease
could influence symptoms I don't know that that was the tricky one for me no no that's
okay that's excellent that's absolutely fine because disease has a relationship with symptoms
it can be determined by symptoms but rain influencing road condition has also a relationship
so it could be a directed compatibility among neighboring image pixels is undirected exactly
it's undirected relationship among connected people are undirected yes until you prove
it a sequence of neighboring word levels is undirected correct component failure influencing
warning signals is directed because it has a relationship it looks like yeah excellent
so it means you have understood the lecture very well and everything is going perfectly
fine isn't it yes looking at that because I did a bit of reading that's 16.2 so based
on that I was able to get a bit of gist on what could be the directed and the undirected
one which characteristics might may influence the outcome okay excellent excellent here
excellent very good because I thought this exercise would be very engaging and I loved
it your responses yeah so
so structure prediction how classification and structure prediction are different there's
a one basic difference in classification you have one label for each and everything x relationship
with y like email is spam or not spam whereas structure prediction can have a several related
outputs sorry I was trying to type at the last moment I just edited this equation so
anyway I will make it clear but this is clear y1 y2 dash dash dash yn so it was basically
y1 y2 dash dash yn means there could be a possibly too many labels because it is a sentence
label for every word whereas classification is just a one one relation it could be multiple
but it could be at a time one but here it could be at a time many so output level must
be considered together because they influence one another so structured prediction like
part of speech tagging there could be one grammatical label per word whereas speech
recognition there could be an ordered sequence of words handwritten recognition an ordered
sequence of characters so we are just trying to discuss this part in ordered output sentence
like machine translation biological sequence analyzers could have a label for each sequence
position so the output is not a single independent prediction it has an internal structure like
consider we discussed this part in nlp where when we discussed natural language processing
like consider the sentence time flies like an arrow so time is a down flies is a verb
like is a proposition and is a determinant arrow is a noun so appropriate label for each
word depends partly on neighboring words and levels means you cannot be just adding up
one level there could be as multiple levels and a structure prediction model's relationship
among the output levels so and then can predict the next word and uh what could be the next
result uh connecting this was observed in latent variables so observed variables are
like image pixels words and latent variables are object parts like hidden topics disease
state uh speaker intention so there is again both relationship between observed data and
output based on the latent structure
I was adding some uh activities this is here yeah
so what are the advantages and challenges when we are presenting structure based models
that could be direct graphs and uh indirect graphs so they can clearly represent relationship
challenges graph structure may be difficult to design and handles uncertainty it could
be incorrect assumptions can mislead the model it uses conditional independence the primary
question is are we using uh graph based models for generative AI better we discuss the import
this direct question are we are graphical models used in the development of deep learning
based applications.
uh.
and are we using them for uh yeah we have already responded generative AI based development
or applications I was just curious to know uh how you are seeing this relevance uh relevance
of these applications uh relevance of this topic
I think that uh in my experience given that the way that uh they're being able to uh consistently
enhance the experience on gathering context it has been very positive when I compare two
years ago to last year to this year the change has been very different and um I could see
a very clear uh evolution pattern on how they're able to recognize patterns and act on those
patterns of context excellent excellent thank you uh I have uh some activities uh based
on today's discussion uh you may consider your assessment three and identify the main
observed variables uh any possible latent variables hidden variables a relationship
among variables whether the relationships are directed or undirected like an agriculture
project that was shared by the candidate or your sentiment analysis uh our output to be
predicted whether the output has an internal structure how a graphical model could support
the neural network and one modeling assumption that would require justification you can consider
these uh uh this design uh uh activity you can consider it and you can maybe respond
on discussion forum or you can solve or answer it at your own time but I have added just
to give you a flavor that would structured probabilistic modeling add genuine value to
your project yes or no it's not necessary but it could be so you just have to check
what is the value of probabilistic more structure probabilistic modeling in your project the
other thing that I have added is a generative AI critical uh critical analysis of generative
AI response so you can add a design a graphical model for a medical diagnosis system using
disease symptoms patient history and test result and you have to add the disease symptoms
and patient disease are just write this one and then evaluate the proposed model based
on these questions so this activity is again you have to relate what you have learned today
and how this generative AI took this response me and this activity I would uh like everyone
should respond on discussion forum you can choose one question or all and why do both
directed and direct graphical models exist how can a structure called as modest support
deep learning select a real world problem and explain how a graphical model could represent
its variables and relationships it could be your own assessment three project or anything
else so just write in your own words uh the response of one or all the questions I can
maybe I can get this over here this is all about today's lecture and what relationship
does your model need to understand not merely predict uh maybe in your uh Lewis for example
in your project the main thing was understanding the relationship between a positive and negative
attributes or maybe the words so you can describe based on your own understanding you know I
would appreciate if you could write a reflection on discussion forum do you have any further
questions or anything you would like to know oh good thank you for the lecture
and are you going okay with the group project I mean any issues or anything you would like
to report for the group project or any difficulties
no I'm on the group who is one and victor and on our case we are progressing well we
have been working on the code and on the report and I we have divided well the rows I think
so on our on our case is progressing solid.